A Finding Aid to the Lilian Swann Saarinen Papers, 1920-1977, in the Archives of American Art AAA.saarlili
Archives of American Art
- Diaries, 1930-1973; Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 3-5, 8
  Saarinen was a prolific journal writer and her diaries are in bound volume and loose leaf form. Bound diary volumes from 1930/1931 to 1942 document her life from her "coming out year" and continue through the early years of her marriage to Eero Saarinen. Her 1939 diary opens in Florence, Italy, in August 1939, days before Germany's invasion of Poland, and describes the tenuous situation the newlyweds found themselves in and their difficulties finding passage back to the United States. The diary labeled 1936 and 1937 appears to span the years 1935-1938 and also contains a series of entries for 1958-1959.
  Loose diary entries, beginning around circa 1934 and continuing to 1953, with scattered additional entries in the 1950s-1970s, focus primarily on Saarinen's marriage to Eero Saarinen. They document in depth her emotional struggles as a working mother attempting to forge her own artistic identity, maintain a healthy family environment for her children, and support Eero Saarinen's growing international success while not allowing that to stymie her own artistic ambitions. These folders include many handwritten notes and drafts of "letters" to Eero Saarinen which are journalistic in nature and include dream journals, "writings and ravings just before wedding," and notes found with her diaries.
  Saarinen's engagement calendars are heavily annotated with notes documenting her professional appointments as well as her personal and leisure activities and those of her family.
  - Addresses, circa 1940s-circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Bound Diary Volume, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bound Diary Volume, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Bound Diary Volume, 1958-1959; 1935-1938 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Bound Diary Volume, 1939 September-1942 January (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Diary of Greece and the Dalmation Coast, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1938, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1940, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1942, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1949, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1951, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1953, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1958, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13-19)
  - Loose Diary Entries and Fragments, circa 1934-1948 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 4
  - Loose Diary Entries and Fragments, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous Fragments, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes Found with Diaries, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Notes Found with Diaries, circa 1954-1969 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes Written Prior to Wedding, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Loose Diary Entries and Fragments from Box 4, Folder 20 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Project Files, 1931-1966; Series 5; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 5-6, 8, OVs 20-23
  Project files are arranged alphabetically by name of project.
  Project files document Saarinen's work on a variety of commissions including those for book cover designs, federal government buildings, post offices, schools and playgrounds, in particular the Crow Island School reliefs, companies such as KLM (then Royal Dutch Airlines), businesses such as Toffenetti's restaurant in Chicago, and private clients including sister-in-law, Pipsan Saarinen. The majority of the projects documented here resulted in fully realized commissions for Saarinen, although several represent ideas and proposals.
  Project files typically contain any and all of the following: correspondence and notes, many preliminary sketches, plans and blueprints, and photographs of artwork and project sites, with the bulk of the material being in the form of sketches. Sketches are primarily in pencil, although some are hand-colored with ink and/or paint.
  - Addison Gallery, Hippo Sketches, circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Barn Dance, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Barns, Katrina McCormick Sculpture, circa 1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bloomfield, Indiana, Post Office, circa 1941 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 5
  - Book Cover for New Directions in Prose and Poetry, circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Book Cover for The White Mule, circa 1931 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Book Ideas for Farrar & Rinehart, circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Carlisle, Kentucky, Post Office Sculpture, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Carlisle, Kentucky, Post Office Sculpture, Sketches, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
  - Ceramic Pig, circa 1941-circa 1943 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 6
  - Children's Magazine ( Child Life?), Chipmunks, circa 1961 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Children's Playground, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Crow Island School, Winnetka, Illinois, File List, circa 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Crow Island School, Winnetka, Illinois, Sketches and Notes, A-Z, circa 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 27-35)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 7 and OV 20
  - Cushion Ideas, circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Evanston, Illinois, Post Office, circa 1939 (Box 5, Folder 37-39)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 8 and OV 21
  - Federal Trade Commission (Apex) Building, Washington D. C., circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 9
  - Gateway Arch, St. Louis, Missouri, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 10
  - Harbor National Bank Clock, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 43-45)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 11
  - KLM Airlines Sculpture, JFK Airport, circa 1947 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 12 and OV 21
  - Museum of Modern Art Competition, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Northland Center, Detroit, Michigan, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 48-50)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 13 and OV 21
  - Red Cross, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 14
  - Rome Collaborative Ideas, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Saarinen, Pipsan, Fireplace, circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
  - Toffenetti's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois, circa 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 56-59)
    Includes photo of Saarinen working on sculpture; oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 15 and OVs 22 and 23
  - Various Project Sketches, circa 1940s-circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 16
  - War Department Competition, circa 1939 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Oversized Bloomfield, Indiana, Post Office from Box 5, Folder 15 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Ceramic Pig from Box 5, Folder 23 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Crow Island School, Winnetka, IL from Box 5, Folders 27-35 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Evanston, Illinois, Post Office from Box 5, Folders 37-39 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Federal Trade Commission (Apex) Building, Washington D. C. from Box 5, Folders 40-41 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Gateway Arch, St. Louis, Missouri from Box 5, Folder 42 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Harbor National Bank Clock from Box 5, Folders 43-45 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Oversized KLM Airlines Sculpture, JFK Airport from Box 5, Folder 46 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Oversized Northland Center, Detroit, Michigan from Box 5, Folders 48-50 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Red Cross from Box 5, Folder 51-52 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Toffenetti's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois from Box 5, Folder 56-59 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Various Project Sketches from Box 6, Folder 1 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Oversized Crow Island School, Winnetka, Illinois from Box 5, Folders 27-35 (Box OV 20)
  - Oversized Evanston, Illinois, Post Office from Box 5, Folders 37-39 (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized KLM Airlines Sculpture, JFK Airport from Box 5, Folder 46 (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized Northland Center, Detroit, Michigan from Box 5, Folders 48-50 (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized Toffenetti's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois from Box 5, Folders 56-59 (Box OV 22)
  - Oversized Toffenetti's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois from Box 5, Folders 56-59 (Box OV 23)
- Teaching Files, 1966-1970; Series 6; 3 Folders Box 6
  This series consists of 3 folders relating to a course Saarinen taught at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and the Cambridge Art Center entitled "The Language of Clay." Found are correspondence and memoranda, course descriptions, notes, and student rosters.
  - Language of Clay Course, Cambridge Art Center, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Language of Clay Course, M. I. T., 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
- Financial Records, 1940s-1970s; Series 7; 2 Folders Box 6
  Series consists of invoices and receipts for supplies and other art-related expenses, records of book royalties for Who Am I? from Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc., and miscellaneous receipts. Also found are records documenting exhibition related expenses, and two catalogs for 1944 and 1956 Saarinen exhibitions, marked with prices.
  - Exhibition Sales and Expenses, 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1940s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, circa 1930s-1970s; Series 8; 0.2 Linear feet Box 6
  Series includes announcements and catalogs for two Saarinen exhibitions as well as some for other artists, many of which are annotated with comments by Saarinen stating her opinion of the artist featured. Also found are copies of a book jacket for The Americans: A New History of the People of the United States (Little Brown and Company, 1963) by Oscar Handlin, the jacket design for which includes a photo of a brass eagle by Saarinen.
  Printed material also includes a group of source files of clippings primarily featuring photos of animals, arranged alphabetically by animal, some news clippings about Saarinen and the Saarinen family, and a folder of news articles on miscellaneous subjects of interest to Saarinen.
  - Announcements and Catalogs, Saarinen, 1948-1960s (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, 1940s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - News Clippings, 1950s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - News Clippings About Saarinen and Family, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Source Material Index, circa 1930s-circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Source Material, B-Z, circa 1930s-circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 16-21)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1909-1974; Series 9; 2 Folders Boxes 6, 9
  Series includes a family scrapbook of clippings about Saarinen's father, Dr. Arhur Swann, concerning his bee cures for rheumatism, as well as his marriage to Saarinen's mother, Susan Sedgwick.
  The Saarinen scrapbook compiles letters, telegrams, newsclippings, announcements and other printed material documenting Saarinen's career from 1935-1974.
  - Family Scrapbook, circa 1909 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Saarinen Scrapbook, 1935-1974 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Oversized volume housed in Box 9, Folder 1
  - Oversized Saarinen Scrapbook from Box 6, Folder 23 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Artwork, circa 1920s-circa 1960s; Series 10; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 6-7, 9-10, OVs 16-18, 24-31
  Artwork consists of Saarinen's sketches in pencil, crayon, ink, pastel and watercolor that did not appear to be arranged as part of her project files. It includes early sketches dating from her childhood to her college years, and subsequent sketches from the 1940s-1960s. Subjects are primarily animals such as cats, dogs, eagles, horses, lions, panthers (including the Jungle Book character Bagheera), and wolves. Also found are anatomy and figure sketches and a series of sketches executed on a trip to Mexico in 1938.
  - Abstract Sketches, circa 1945-circa 1955 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 2 and OV 24
  - Anatomy Sketches, circa 1929-1930s (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Oversized material housed in OV 24
  - Animal Prints, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Animal Sketches, circa 1920s-circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 27-31)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folders 3-5, Box 10, Folders 1-4, and OVs 16 and 24-28
  - Animal Sketches, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 32-33)
  - Animal Sketches, Eagles, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 34-39)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 5-6 and OV 17
  - Animal Sketches, Pekingese, Poodles, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 40-41)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 7
  - Animal Sketches, Pelicans, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 8
  - Animal Sketches, Skunk, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Animal Sketches, Three-Toed Sloth, circa 1939 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Early Sketches, 1920s (Box 6, Folder 46-53)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 9-10 and OV 18
  - Figure Sketches, 1929-circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 11-13 and OV 29-30
  - Future Sculpture Ideas, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 55)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 14
  - Jewelry Designs, circa 1955 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Line Drawings, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Mexico Trip Sketches, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches, circa 1920s-circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 15
  - Mowgli, Bagheera and Baloo Sketches, circa 1936-1940s (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Oversized material housed in OV 31
  - "Sketch for Dead Chamois", circa 1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Abstract Sketches from Box 6, Folder 24 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folder 27-31 (Box 9, Folder 3-5)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Eagles from Box 6, Folder 34-39 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Pekingese, from Box 6, Folders 40-41 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Pelicans from Box 6, Folders 42-43 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Early Sketches from Box 6, Folder 46-53 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Oversized Figure Sketches from Box 6, Folder 54 (Box 10, Folder 11-13)
  - Oversized Future Sculpture Ideas from Box 6, Folder 55 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Sketches from Box 7, Folders 3-4 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folder 27-31 (Box OV 16)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Eagles from Box 6, Folders 34-39 (Box OV 17)
  - Oversized Early Sketches from Box 6, Folders 46-53 (Box OV 18)
  - Oversized Abstract Sketches from Box 6 Folder 24 (Box OV 24)
  - Oversized Anatomy Sketches from Box 6, Folder 25 (Box OV 24)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box OV 24)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box OV 25)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box OV 26)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box OV 27)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches from Box 6, Folders 27-31 (Box OV 28)
  - Oversized Figure Sketches from Box 6, Folder 54 (Box OV 29)
  - Oversized Figure Sketches from Box 6, Folder 54 (Box OV 30)
  - Oversized Mowgli, Bagheera and Baloo Sketches from Box 7, Folder 5 (Box OV 31)
- Photographs, circa 1940s, 1977; Series 11; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 7, 11, OV 31
  Photos of Saarinen and others include a negative of a photograph of Saarinen, possibly with Eero Saarinen included with a 1977 letter of transmittal; a group photograph including Lilian, Eero and Eliel Saarinen with the model for the Detroit Civic Center; and a photo of an unidentified woman on a city street.
  Also found are photos of artwork executed by Saarinen, and photos by Betty Cooper of Saarinen's 1944 exhibtion at G Place Gallery.
  - Photos of Saarinen and Others, circa 1940s, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photos of Artwork, circa 1930s-circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folders 1-5 and OV 31
  - Photos of Exhibition Installation, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 6
  - Oversized Photos of Artwork from Box 7, Folder 8 (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
  - Oversized Photos of Exhibition Installation from Box 7, Folder 9 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Photos of Artwork from Box 7, Folder 8 (Box OV 31)